Guide to the History of Medicine artifacts collection, 1550-1980s RL.10155
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
History of Medicine artifacts collection
1550-1980s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
History of Medicine Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
RL.10155
51.5 Linear Feet about 851 items
Collection consists of historical medical instruments and artifacts, art objects, realia, and other three-dimensional objects related to the history of medicine, primarily originating from Europe and the United States, but including some artifacts from China and Japan. Ranging in age from the late 16th to the late 20th centuries, objects include medical kits and pharmaceutical items (often in the original cases and bags); equipment used in amputation, obstetrics, opthalmology, surgery, urology, neurology, early electrical therapies, and in research and diagnostic settings; instructional objects such as anatomical models and figurines; and other objects such as apothecary jars, cupping glasses, infant feeders, a bas-relief memento mori, and fetish figures. There are many models of microscopes and stethoscopes, dating from the 17th to the 20th century. Accquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Access Restrictions
Access note. Collection contains fragile materials which may involve extra assistance from staff. Types of items include glass, ceramics, rare instruments, or other vulnerable materials. Contact Research Services with questions.
Provenance
The History of Medicine artifacts collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2011. Additions to the collection were received as gifts in 2021 and 2023.
Historical Note
The History of Medicine Collections artifacts collections began in 1956 with the donation of the Josiah C. Trent Collection, which formed the nucleus of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke Unversity's Medical Library. The Trent family's donation included many artifacts related to the practice of medicine. Subsequent acquisitions over the years from many other donors make up the rest of this collection, which forms part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University. The collection continues to receive additions.
Collection Overview
Collection consist of historical medical instruments and artifacts, art objects, realia, and other three-dimensional objects, primarily originating from Europe and the United States, but including some artifacts from China and Japan. Ranging in age from the late 16th to the late 20th centuries, objects include physician's medical kits and pharmaceutical items (often in the original cases and bags); clinical equipment used in amputation, obstetrics, opthalmology, surgery, neurology, early electrical therapies, and in research and diagnostic settings; instructional objects such as anatomical models; and art objects such as apothecary jars, a bas-relief memento mori, a marble skull, and fetish figures.
There are many models of microscopes, from a small monocular "flea glass" to mid-20th century models. Other early medical instruments and supplies include amputation saws, bleeding bowls, cupping glasses, hypodermic needles, infant and invalid feeders, lancets, opthalmoscopes, pill rollers, stethoscopes, syringes, and other items. A more unusual item - and one of the larger pieces - is an adult walker made of wood, dating perhaps to the 19th century or earlier.
Of interest is a large collection of early anatomical and diagnostic human models from China and continental Europe, in the shape of small, intricately detailed manikins, most crafted from ivory. Some feature removable anatomical parts, and female figures often include a removable fetus. There is also a model illustrating acupuncture points. Other instructional artifacts include glass slides used in medical school lectures.
Most of these objects were photographed by Medical Library staff; at a later time, digital images of almost all of the objects in the collection were added to the online Duke University Historical Images in Medicine database, linked in this collection guide and now available through the Duke Digital Repository. Many of the original black-and-white photographic prints are filed in the History of Medicine Picture File collection. See the Related Materials section in this collection guide for links to these resources.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged by donor's last name, and within by the unique identifier assigned to each object by library staff. Items of unknown or uncertain provenance are listed in a large "Anonymous" category following the named collections.
Related Material
History of Medicine Picture File
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Historical Images in Medicine (HIM) Database
Medical Center Library, Duke University
Medicine -- History; Medicine -- Study and teaching; Medical instruments and apparatus -- United States -- History; Medicine -- Europe -- History; Microscopes; Medicine -- United States -- History; Medicine bottles; Physicians -- United States -- History; Surgery -- History; Surgical instruments and apparatus; Obstetrics -- Apparatus and instruments; Opthalmology -- Equipment and supplies; Pharmacology -- History; Phlebotomy -- Equipment and supplies; Apothecary jars; Amputation -- Equipment and supplies; Models, Anatomic; Neurology -- Equipment and supplies; Medical instruments and apparatus -- History; Manikins; Human anatomy -- Models -- Early works to 1800; Cupping -- Equipment and supplies
- W. Banks Anderson, Jr. Collection Artifacts, 19th century-1950s, 31 items
  Scope and Contents note
  Artifacts donated by W. Banks Anderson, Jr., MD.
  - Zeiss compound monocular microscope (Artifact-box 160, Item hander0002)
    Zeiss compound monocular microscope with mechanical stage. Signed: Carl Zeiss, Jena, No. 41871. Brass and black laquer on a cast-iron base. This microscope has the jug handle design which was introduced in 1898. Basically a hand grip was added to the limb of the microscope; at its best, the handle was integrated and sleek. The style did not last long and ended before 1920. White lettering on the cast-iron horseshoe base indicates the microscope once belonged to Dr. Frederic Moir Hanes, chair of the Department of Medicine.
    Dr. Carl Zeiss founded a business in Jena, Germany and began making microscopes in 1847. His was the dominant optical firm in the world from the beginning of the 20th century through 1945 when it was seperated into two firms following partition of Germany after World War II. Many firms have been associated with the Zeiss firm and have produced Zeiss products under license or as partners. Bausch & Lomb, which originated in Rochester, NY in 1853, was among those.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Received from: W. Banks Anderson, Jr., MD
  - 11 pairs of spectacles and eyeglasses (Artifact-box 202, Item hander0004)
    11 pairs of eyeglasses and spectacles: 1. "Harlequin" style with rhinestone frames. 1950s. 2. Spectacles, wire-rimmed 3. Spectacles, wire-rimmed 4. Pince-nez spectacles; round glass, silver frame. With case. 5. Bifocals; oval glass, gold frames. With case. 6. Pince-nez spectacles; oval glass, no frame, chain missing. With case. 7. Reverse half glasses (distance only); silver frame. With case. 8. Spectacles; round glass, silver frame with incised design. With case. 9. Bifocals; round glass, no frame, silver chain with hook. With case. 10. Pince-nez spectacles; oval glass, no frame, chain missing. With case. 11. Pince-nez spectacles; round glass, gold frame. With case.
  - Glass contact lenses, 20th century (Artifact-box 196, Item hander0005)
    Cornealschalen fur Lichtkoagulator. Ten glass lenses in wooden case.
    Contact lenses were delivered with Duke Medical Center's first light coagulator (1950s?). Doris Duke donated the money for it. The machine was invented by Gerd Meyer Schwickernath.
  - Ophthalmology instruments (Artifact-box 199, Item hander0006)
    Ophthalmology instruments: four ivory handled instruments, marked Tiemann. Two stainless steel handled instruments, marked Germany: KNY-Scheerer. Wooden case with Tiemann label. New York: George Tiemann & Co. Instruments are from several different date ranges. George Tiemann & Co. has supplied surgical instruments since 1826.
- Cathy Angell Collection Artifacts, 20th century, approx. 5 items
  Donated by Cathy Angell
  - Compound binocular microscope, after 1920s (Artifact-box 362, Item hangel0001, Artifact-box 366)
    Compound binocular microscope. Black case with accessories. Signed: Spencer, Buffalo, USA.
    Received from: Cathy Angell
- Beyer Family Collection Artifacts, 18th century-circa 1935, approx. 135 items
  Artifacts donated by Dr. and Mrs. Emil C. Beyer.
  - Box mount microscope, approximately 1825 (Artifact-box 152, Item hbeyer0001)
    Compound monocular. Unsigned. Brass with wooden carrying case. The microscope attaches to a brass fitting on the top of the case which then acts as a base. Accessories included are brass opticals, a bull's-eye condenser, and ivory specimen slides.
    In the 18th century there was a demand for microscopes which could be kept in a small space and carried into the field. The "pack-away" microscope reached its heyday between 1790 and 1830. Such instruments were made for the amateur market since no serious microscopist would want to keep dismantling his instrument. The Cary-type microscope came in a limited variety of sizes. This is one of the larger versions.
    Received from: Dr. and Mrs. Emil C. Beyer
  - Mortar and pestle, undated (Artifact-box 302, Item hbeyer0003)
    Wood mortar and pestle. Decorative carved horizontal lines run around the outside of the mortar.
  - Medicine chest, undated (Artifact-box 274, Item hbeyer0004)
    Small flip-top mahogany chest with brass handle and one drawer. Accessories include empty glass bottles, scales and weights.
  - Wyeth's Granular Effervescing Lithium Citrate patent medicine bottle, undated (Artifact-box 113, Item hbeyer0005)
    Philadelphia: John Wyeth & Brother [n.d.] Blue glass bottle with glass cap. Original paper label.
  - Medicine cup, undated (Artifact-box 108, Item hbeyer0006)
    Glass medicine cup in a round wooden case. Cup is marked for dosage: tea, dessert, table.
  - Infant feeder, approx. 1820 (Artifact-box 189, Item hbeyer0007)
    Staffordshire pottery decorated in blue transfer-printed design.
  - Medium infant or invalid feeder, undated (Artifact-box 110, Item hbeyer0008)
    Medium infant or invalid feeder. Ceramic with gold leaf trim. Multicolored floral design.
  - Large infant or invalid feeder, undated (Artifact-box 115, Item hbeyer0009)
    Ceramic with gold leaf trim. Multicolored floral design.
  - Infant or invalid feeder, undated (Artifact-box 111, Item hbeyer0010)
    Ceramic. Blue floral design.
  - Nursing can or mammele, late 18th-mid 19th century (Artifact-box 12, Item hbeyer0011)
    Made in Pennsylvania: tin, with flip top, handle at right angle to spout.
  - Double-ended medicine spoon, 19th century (Artifact-box 109, Item hbeyer0012)
    Pewter. Hinged for portability. The spoons are different sizes for two sizes of dose.
  - Graduated cordial-style medicine glasses, undated (Artifact-box 114, Item hbeyer0013)
    Ruby colored blown glass with etched grape vines.
  - Infant or invalid feeder, undated (Artifact-box 112, Item hbeyer0014)
    Ceramic. White on white raised floral design around the mouth of the feeder.
  - Infant or invalid feeder, undated (Artifact-box 10, Item hbeyer0015)
    White glazed pottery shaped to resemble a duck.
  - Portable electrocardiograph, 1935? (Box 96, Item hbeyer0016)
    "Simpli-trol" Portable Model Cambridge Electrocardiograph No. 0-0195503. In wooden case with metal latches; brass label identifies the original owner. Made for Henry A. Rogan, MD by the Cambridge Instrument Co., Inc.
  - Collection of cupping glasses, undated (Artifact-box 67, Item hbeyer0018)
    Examples of both blown and molded glasses.
  - Wooden walker, American, 19th century? (Item hbeyer0019)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Please contact the Curator for the History of Medicine Collections directly to view item.
  - Piorry monaural stethoscope, early 19th century (Artifact-box 175, Item hbeyer0020)
    Wood with ivory earpiece.
  - Bloodletting fleam in leather case, undated (Artifact-box 174, Item hbeyer0021)
    Fleam has three blades.
  - Dissection set, 19th century (Artifact-box 43, Item hbeyer0022)
    Nine-piece post-mortem dissecting set in wooden case by Wood & Son, Manchester, England; includes saw and hammer. Additional ivory handled pieces by Gary and Lawson.
  - O'Dwyer's apparatus for intubation, approximately 1880 (Artifact-box 11, Item hbeyer0023)
    Apparatus for intubation of the larynx in case of diptheria. Gold-plated tubes of various sizes depending on the needs of the child; in velvet-lined wooden box with padded silk lid.
  - Sterilizer, undated (Artifact-box 250, Item hbeyer0024)
    Elliptical metal box with crowned caduceus on lid.
  - Atomizers, undated (Artifact-box 242, Item hbeyer0025)
    1) Glass vessel with metal sprayer 2) Glass vessel with rubber bulb
  - Eye cup, undated (Artifact-box 352, Item hbeyer0026)
    Glass eye cup
  - Medicine bottle in metal case, undated (Artifact-box 251, Item hbeyer0027)
  - Glass nipple shield, undated (Artifact-box 249, Item hbeyer0028)
  - Dr. John Hooper's female pills, 1743 (Artifact-box 60, Item hbeyer0029)
    Elliptical wooden case with printing on the top of lid. Originally contained 40 pills.
  - Urinals, undated (Artifact-box 383, Item hbeyer0030)
    Two are made of glass and one of pottery.
  - Assorted glassware (Artifact-box 381, Item hbeyer0031, Artifact-box 382)
    Bottles (includes labeled and embossed); patent medicines (in bottles, tins and packages); pharmaceutical measures
  - Marble skull, undated (Artifact-box 252, Item hbeyer0032)
  - Unidentified metal instrument, undated (Artifact-box 243, Item hbeyer0033)
    Made by Boehm Surgical Instrument Corp., Rochester, N.Y. In damaged shagreen case, lined in green velvet.
  - Earthenware inhaler, approximately 1875 (modern replica) (Artifact-box 233, Item hbeyer0034)
    Replica of Maw's double-valved earthenware inhaler. London: S. Maw Son & Thompson
  - Mortar and pestle, approximately late 19th-early 20th century (Artifact-box 275, Item hbeyer0035)
    Made of pottery by B. E. and Co. Best. Item is damaged.
    Used by Bracklo Bros., Apothecaries, 10 Greenwich St., New York
  - Small silver instrument case, undated (Artifact-box 290, Item hbeyer0037)
  - General purpose medical and surgical kit, 19th century (Artifact-box 157, Item hbeyer0038)
    Philadelphia: Charles Lentz & Sons. Includes leather carrying case (straps are broken off); and wooden case with brass fittings.
  - Small medicine case with snap, early 20th century (Artifact-box 294, Item hbeyer0040)
    Contains four empty bottles. Black leather case is damaged.
  - Small medicine case with Red Cross snap, early 20th century (Artifact-box 292, Item hbeyer0041)
    Contains seven empty bottles in black leather case.
  - Rosewood medicine chest, 19th century (Artifact-box 206, Item hbeyer0042)
    Folding rosewood medicine chest with mother of pearl inlay and silver handle made in England. Some damage to wood & inlay. Includes key. Chest contains large glass stoppered bottles (some with contents), mother of pearl balance, brass weights, graduate, funnel, mortar & pestle, and miscellaneous instruments.
  - Surgical instruments in velvet-lined oak case, 18th century (Artifact-box 71, Item hbeyer0044)
    Wooden case with brass fittings, made in England. Damaged: Cover detached. Approximately 18 pieces including two trephines and bone brush.
  - Korseal filling and closing apparatus, probably late 19th century (Artifact-box 159, Item hbeyer0045)
    Wooden box; lid detached. Instructions pasted inside lid. Made for J.M. Grosvenor & Co., Boston, Massachusetts.
  - Homeopathic medicine chest, late 19th century (Artifact-box 208, Item hbeyer0046)
    New York: Boericke Homeopathic Pharmacy. Wooden box with key, containing 61 glass bottles with labels and marked stoppers.
  - Homeopathic medicine chest, late 19th century (Artifact-box 190, Item hbeyer0047)
    Rosewood box with key. Metal inlaid disc is missing from lid. Includes 29 glass vials with labels and contents. Humphrey's Specific Homeopathic Remedies" chart pasted inside lid.
  - Homeopathic medicine chest with drawer, 19th century (Artifact-box 70, Item hbeyer0048)
    Liverpool & Birkenhead: Joseph Marples Homeopathic Chemist. Wood; no key. Contents include 57 glass vials with labels and marked stoppers; three empty vials; six bottles of liquid preparation; one empty bottle. Spatula with wooden handle. Also found in drawer: Nos 8, 37, 40 of Wills's Cigarettes First Aid Series collectible cards.
  - Wooden massager, undated (Artifact-box 282, Item hbeyer0049)
    Wooden roller on metal handle.
  - Tooth key with bone handle and four hooks, undated (Artifact-box 280, Item hbeyer0050)
  - Lactometer, undated (Artifact-box 227, Item hbeyer0053)
    Lactometer for milk in wooden tube.
  - Alcohol lamp in chrome box, undated (Artifact-box 140, Item hbeyer0054)
    Item is pocket-size; stamped on bottom: U.S.A. M.D. Used to disolve powders and pills into solution for injection.
  - Loring's ophthalmoscope, late 19th or early 20th century (Artifact-box 139, Item hbeyer0055)
    Ivory handle; in leather case.
  - Dental care kit, undated (Artifact-box 138, Item hbeyer0057)
    Four steel instruments and one ivory handle, in shagreen-covered case with mirror in lid.
- Daryl Bigner Collection Artifacts, mid-20th century, 2 items
  Artifacts donated by Daryl Bigner, MD.
  - Compound monocular microscope, mid-20th century (Artifact-box 167, Item hbigne0001)
    Brass and black laquer; signed: Bauch & Lomb Optical Co., Rochester, N.Y., USA. Original wooden case; no accessories are included.
    Received from: Daryl Bigner, MD.
- Warren Bird Collection Artifacts, 19th century, 1 items
  Artifact donated by the estate of Warren Bird.
  - Purified talcum powder, 19th century (Artifact-box 293, Item hbird0001)
    Morganton, NC: Spake Pharmacy.
    Received from: The Estate of Warren Bird
- Ronald Bost Collection Artifacts, circa 1890-circa 1915, approx. 20 items
  Artifact donated by Dr. Ronald Bost.
  - Military surgery set, circa 1915 (Artifact-box 53, Item hbost0001)
    Mahogany case with two lift-out trays of surgical instruments. The Kny-Scheerer Co., New York. Includes small packet of sutures from George Tiemann & Co. New York. Plate on top is engraved with "Med Dept. U.S.A."
    Received from: Dr. Ronald Bost
  - Field surgeon's amputation kit, circa 1890 (Artifact-box 52, Item hbost0002)
    Amputation kit in oak case; includes packet of surgical silk cord from Archibald Turner & Co. Case is damaged.
- Ewald Busse Collection Artifacts, 1937 and undated, approx. 20 items
  Artifacts donated by Ewald W. Busse, MD.
  - Ophthalmoscope, undated (Artifact-box 204, Item hbusse0001)
    Bausch & Lomb ophthalmoscope in box with accessories.
    Received from: Ewald W. Busse, MD
  - Hemoglobinometer, 1937 (Artifact-box 238, Item hbusse0002)
    Marked: "Sahli-Adams improved non-fade hemometer. New York: Clay-Adams Co., Inc." Combination hemacytometer and hemometer outfit in box with accessories.
  - Hippocrates plaque, undated (Artifact-box 245, Item hbusse0004)
  - Aesculapius plaque, undated (Artifact-box 246, Item hbusse0005)
  - Hippocrates plaque, undated (Artifact-box 247, Item hbusse0006)
    Depicts a physician with patient.
- Dr. Callaway Collection Artifacts, 18th or 19th century, 3 items
  Artifacts donated by Dr. Callaway.
  - Cupping jar, undated (Artifact-box 221, Item hcalla0001)
    Small metal cupping jar.
    Received from: Dr. Callaway
  - Doctor's sign: Dr. R.G. Barclay, undated (Artifact-box 214, Item hcalla0002)
    Made of metal.
  - Three-blade folding fleam with brass shield, 18th or 19th century (Artifact-box 223, Item hcalla0003)
- Virginia M. Carden Collection Artifacts, late 1940s-early 1950s, 2 items
  Artifacts donated by Virginia M. Carden.
  - Pair of plastic contact lenses in case, late 1940s-early 1950s (Artifact-box 195, Item hcarde0001)
    Originally belonged to Ginger Carden's mother.
    Received from: Virginia M. Carden
- Bayard Carter Collection Artifacts, mid-20th century, approx. 40 items
  Artifacts donated by Bayard Carter, MD.
  - Glass slides for Dr. Carter's obstetrics and gynecology lectures, mid-20th century (Artifact-box 50a, Item hcarte0001, Artifact-box 50b, Artifact-box 51a, Artifact-box 51b)
    Slides include lecture text, historical illustrations, and pathology examples. In two wooden slide boxes.
    Bayard Carter was the first chair of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology at Duke University, 1931-1964.
    Received from: Bayard Carter, MD
- Alphonsus Cobb Collection Artifacts, early to mid-19th century, approx. 5 items
  Artifacts donated by Alphonsus Cobb.
  - Amputation set, early to mid-19th century (Artifact-box 107, Item hcobba0001)
    Civil War amputation set in wooden box with brass plate on lid, engraved with initials: BFC
    Received from: Alphonsus Cobb
- Dr. Wilbert C. Davison Collection Artifacts, 20th century, 2 items
  Artifacts donated by Dr. Wilbert C. Davison
  - Bas-relief sculpture of head of Sir William Osler by Doris Appel, mid-20th century (Artifact-box 235, Item hdavis0001)
    Bas-relief sculpture of head of Sir William Osler by Doris Appel (1904-1995). Lynn, Massachusetts: Doris Appel Medical Sculptures
    Given after Dr. Davison retired to Roaring Gap, N.C.
    Received from: Dr. Wilbert C. Davison
  - Laennec stethoscope, 20th century (Artifact-box 256, Item hdavis0002)
    From Wyeth Laboratories. Small scale replica on wooden stand.
- Dr. Thomas Doxiades Collection Artifacts, undated, 1 items
  Artifacts donated by Dr. Thomas Doxiades
  - Gavel of wood from the plane-tree of Hippocrates, undated (Artifact-box 326, Item hdoxia0001)
    Gavel of wood from the plane-tree of Hippocrates on the Island of Cos.
    Presented to the University Medical Center by Dr. Thomas Doxiades.
    Received from: Dr. Thomas Doxiades
- L.M. Draper Collection Artifacts, 20th century, 108 items
  Artifacts donated by Mrs. L.M. Draper.
  - Collection of medical instruments from the practice of Dr. L.M. Draper, 20th century (Artifact-box 38, Item hdrape0001, Artifact-box 39, Artifact-box 40)
    Collection of 108 medical instruments from the practice of Dr. L.M. Draper. Contents include: Amputation pincers, retractors, syringes, pelvimeter, wooden handle obstetric forceps, wide variety of forceps and specula.
    Many examples are unique to the collection.
    Received from: Mrs. Draper
- Carl T. Durham Collection Artifacts, 19th century, 2 items
  Artifacts donated by Carl T. Durham.
  - Meerschaum pipe, 19th century (Artifact-box 176, Item hdurha0001)
    Pipe has hand-carved bowl. Housed in fitted leather satin-lined case.
    Received from: Carl T. Durham
- Harold P. Erickson Collection Artifacts, 20th century, 1 items
  Artifact donated by Harold P. Erickson, PhD.
  - Simple Leeuwenhoek model microscope, late 17th century (replica) (Artifact-box 7, Item herick0001)
    20th century replica of a Leeuwenhoek microscope, mounted in plexiglass box.
    Gift of Prof. John W. Everett.
    Received from: Harold P. Erickson, PhD
- Bernard F. Fetter Collection Artifacts, 20th century, approx. 30 items
  Artifacts donated by Bernard F. Fetter, MD; William J. Fetter, MD.
  - Pocket hypodermic needle kit, early 20th century (Artifact-box 304, Item hfette0001)